A Guide to the Robert Wiley Collection, 1843-1956
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Robert Wiley Collection, 1843-1956
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 06-21
0.5 linear feet
The Robert Wiley Collection consists of correspondence, ephemera, newspaper clippings, a book and book fragments, and a photocopy of the roll and minutes of the Marr Camp United Confederate Veterans of Fairfax.
Wiley, Robert (1840-1932)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert Wiley’s granddaughter Mary Lee Bryant, October 1994
Historical and Biographical Information
Robert Wiley was born on August 16, 1840, to Joseph and Catherine Wiley in the Mount Vernon District of Fairfax County. He began service with the Confederate army in September 1861 serving as a scout. On March 8, 1862, Wiley enlisted in Company K of the Nineteenth Georgia Infantry at Occoquan in Prince William County. He took part in the battles of Williamsburg, West Point, Seven Pines, Cedar Mountain, Second Manassas, Ox Hill, Harper's Ferry, Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville, Olustee, Drewry's Bluff, and the Seven Days' battles. He was severely wounded multiple times and was briefly captured as a prisoner of war following the Battle of Fredericksburg. He surrendered in Raleigh, North Carolina on April 30, 1865, and returned home on May 20, 1865.
After the war, he served as Justice of the Peace for the Mount Vernon District. He was elected Commissioner of the Revenue for Fairfax County from 1871-1891 and then served as County Treasurer for 24 years. He was the Commander of the John Q. Marr Camp, United Confederate Veterans at Fairfax; vice president of the Lorton Valley Democratic Club; and a trustee of the Fairfax Cemetery Association.
Wiley married Mary Elizabeth Lee, of Fairfax, on June 26, 1867. The couple had seven children. The Wiley family lived in Lorton, Virginia where the present day Wiley Drive is located. He and his family later moved to the Town of Fairfax and lived in the Roberts/Chichester House at 3701 Chain Bridge Road from 1902 until his wife’s death in 1923. Wiley died at his daughter’s house in Fairfax following a long illness on February 13, 1932. He is buried in the Confederate section of the Fairfax Cemetery.
Scope and Content
The Robert Wiley Collection consists of correspondence, ephemera, newspaper clippings, a book and book fragments, and a photocopy of the roll and minutes of the Marr Camp United Confederate Veterans of Fairfax. Correspondence to fellow Confederate veterans include James Madison Arnold of Barstow County, GA.; J. Ryland Epps of Richmond, VA.; William Selwyn Ball of McLean, VA.; Abraham V. Sager of Vienna, VA.; James M. Love of Fairfax, VA.; Leonidas Rosser Houchens of Fairfax, VA.; Isaac A. Roe of Calhoun, GA.; and John Coxe of Groveland, CA. Also included are correspondence with John B. Webster of Lorton, VA (postmaster of Springman, VA. and later Lorton, VA.); Maude A. Harnsberger, wife of Rev. Alfred L. Harnsberger; and state senator R. Walton Moore. Of particular note is an original postcard of the Willcoxon Hotel in Fairfax, VA.; a page from a family Bible that notes the marriage date of Daniel McCarty Fitzhugh and Sinah Ellen Chichester Lee; and an 1843 letter from John Cadle of Marion County, MO to his brother-in-law Edward L. Bates of Lorton, VA.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Fairfax County Office of County Treasurer 1893-1894 Tax Account Book, MSS 09-22
Original Marr Camp U.C.V. record book and other collectibles owned by Robert Wiley donated to the Fairfax City Museum
Index Terms
Arnold, James M. (1843-1912); Ball, William Selwyn (1846-1932); Bates, Edward L. (1796-1864); Cadle, John (1799-1850); Coxe, John (1845-?); Epps, J. Ryland (1843-?); Fairfax (Va.) - History; Fitzhugh, Daniel McCarty (1802-1881); Harnsberger, Maude Atkins (1877-1962); Houchens, Leonidas Rosser (1844-1933); Lee, Sinah Ellen Chichester (1806-1887); Lorton (Va.) - History; Love, James Monroe (1842-1933); Marr Camp (Fairfax, Va.); Moore, R. Walton (1859-1941); Roe, Isaac A. (1837-1921); Sager, Abraham V. (1848-1930); Veterans - Virginia - Fairfax County - Registers; Webster, John B. (1850-1926); Wiley, Robert (1840-1932)
Container List
- Roll and Records, Marr Camp, United Confederate Veterans, 1908-1929 [Photocopy], 1908-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Lyrics sheet, “The Battle of Manassas” Miss Mary E. Lee’s song written by Mr. Athey, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Poem, “Farewell to Johnsons Island” Copy by W.P. Moncure,, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Newspaper clippings regarding Marr Camp U.C. V. and a fragment of a wedding dress, 1928-1956, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter, J.M. Arnold to Robert Wiley, 1902 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letter, J.M. Arnold to Robert Wiley, 1906 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letter, J.M. Arnold to Robert Wiley, 1909 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letter, J. Ryland Epps to Robert Wiley, 1911 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letter, Corinne M. to Robert Wiley [letter mentions Titanic sinking], 1912 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letter, John Coxe to Robert Wiley [mentions skirmish at Colchester], 1915 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letter, Corinne M. to Mr. & Mrs. Robert Wiley, 1918 December 21 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letter, J.B. Webster to Robert Wiley, 1919 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letter, R. Walton Moore to Robert Wiley [includes forwarded letter from William Beverley of Broad Run, Va.], 1922 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letter, J.M. Love to Robert Wiley, 1926 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Letter, William S. Ball to Robert Wiley, 1927 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letter, I.A. Rowe, Capt. Company K of 19th Georgia Infantry to Editor of the Fairfax Herald, c. 1927 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Letter, L.R. Houchens to Robert Wiley, 1928 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Postcard of Shenandoah Valley, Mrs. A.L. Harnsberger to Robert Wiley, 1928 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Letter, A.V. Sager to Robert Wiley, 1929 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Postcard of Willcoxon Fairfax Hotel, Fannie to Mrs. Robert Wiley, 1929 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Bible Page, Marriage of Daniel M. Fitzhugh to Ellen Lee (June 30, 1830), Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Letter, John Cadle to E.L. Bates, Occoquan, Va., 1843 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Invitation, Daniel McC. Lee to Columbian Literary Society Anniversary Celebration, 1857 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Deed, Robert and Mary Wiley to John W. Cranford, 1879 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Letter transcript, George Washington to Peter Wagoner (11/20/1781) copied by E.R. Holbrook, 1902 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Book fragment, “Wearing of the Gray” by John Eston Cooke pp. 585-598,, c. 1867 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Book, “Historical Collections of Virginia” by Henry Howe (Babcock & Co.) [missing pp. 1-96], 1845 (Box 1, Folder 27)